Guide to the Visual AIDS Records MSS.503
Fales Library and Special Collections
Visual AIDS Records
1986-2025, ongoing
1989-2000
Fales Library and Special Collections
Visual AIDS (Organization)
MSS.503
60 Linear Feet in 65 manuscript boxes, 5 small manuscript boxes, 8 oversized flat boxes, 11 flat-file folders, and various items within 6 shared boxes.
176.60 Megabytes in 80 computer files
11 websites in 11 archived websites.
11 audiocassettes
1 U-matic
2 Betacam
5 VHS
Visual AIDS is a New York City-based contemporary arts organization committed to HIV/AIDS prevention and awareness whose mission is accomplished through projects which support artists living with the disease, as well as honor and preserve the legacies of artists who have died from this disease. This collection documents an organization formed as a reaction to the AIDS crisis during the late 1980s through the lens of the artistic community and their active response at that time and the proceeding decades. The Visual AIDS Records (1986-2025, ongoing) document the daily administrative activities of the organization since its inception in 1988, as well as documenting the organization's key initiatives including a Day With(out) Art, Electric Blanket, and The Archive Project. Materials within this collection include archived websites, correspondence, Board meeting minutes, notes, press clippings, press kits, press clippings, memorabilia, calendars, and video and audio recordings related to events. This collection also contains promotional brochures, forms, and posters for exhibitions, benefit events, and general programming, as well as collectible broadside graphic art posters created by various artists which were distributed to organizations and used as a promotional tool for the organization. A small selection of individual artists' files contained in this collection typically include artist statements, press clippings, resumes, as well as artwork images in the form of slides and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Nelson Santos on behalf of Visual AIDS in late June 2017. The accession number associated with this gift is 2017.179.
http://visualaids.org/, https://vava.visualaids.org/, https://dwa.visualaids.org/, https://postcards.visualaids.org/, https://secure.givelively.org/donate/visual-aids-for-the-arts-inc/vava-voom-2020-not-business-as-usual/, http://vava2021.visualaids.org/, https://dwa2021.visualaids.org/, https://sites.google.com/visualaids.org/dwa2022/, and https://video.visualaids.org/ were initially selected as part of the NYC Arts Community COVID-19 Response Web Collection in May 2020-October 2022. In October 2022, crawling of the seeds were discontinued in NYC Arts Community COVID-19 Response Web Collection and crawling began in the Visual AIDS Web Collection. The website was captured through the use of Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. The accession numbers associated with these websites are 2022.051 and 2023.020. In November 2023, https://www.oralhistories.visualaids.org/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2023.060. In May 2024, https://art-aids-action.tumblr.com/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2024.024.
Appraisal
In January 2022, curators reappraised and discarded a suitcase that arrived with the collection.
In 2025, the following were removed from the collection during processing: duplicates of publications, fliers, and press clippings; 2 t-shirts; 2 bowling shirts; 5 cloth tote bags; 88 VHS, 3 DVD, 2 U-Matic, 2 audiocassettes (these were either off-air or commercial recordings); and 19 born-digital carriers (duplicates of existing paper material in the collection). Multiple packets of lube and condoms were removed from the collection at the suggestion of conservators due to the fact that these items were not unique and that they had the possibility of damaging nearby items if their enclosures were to rupture. A small number of artists' individual files were removed from the collection after notes within the files indicated they did not wish their files to remain in the collection.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Arrangement
Organized into five series, one of which is arranged into subseries:
Series I. Administrative Records
Series II. Projects and Exhibitions
Series III. Day With(out) Art
Series IV. Electric Blanket
Series V. The Archive Project
Subseries V.A. Project Documentation
Subseries V.B. Exhibitions
Subseries V.C. Artists' Files
Material within each series is arranged chronologically and grouped by subject, with the exception of Subseries V.C., which is arranged in alphabetical order.
Historical Note
Visual AIDS is a New York-based nonprofit founded in 1988 by curators and critics William Olander, Robert Atkins, Thomas Sokolowski, and Gary Garrels. The organization uses art to raise awareness of HIV/AIDS and supports artists living with the virus. Visual AIDS preserves the work of HIV+ artists and honors the cultural contributions of the AIDS movement through art exhibitions, public forums, and publications. Visual AIDS also organizes Day With(out) Art, an annual event that encourages arts organizations worldwide to raise awareness about HIV/AIDS. The nonprofit collaborates with galleries and art institutions, supports the creation of new artwork, and provides a platform for community-building within safe spaces.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Fales Library and Special Collections, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Related Materials
For additional information on this organization's records and artists' files, Visual AIDS maintains their own archives and Artists' Registry: https://visualaids.org/projects/the-artist-registry-and-archive-project
Scope and Contents
The Visual AIDS Records (1986–2025, ongoing) document the administrative and programming activities of Visual AIDS, a contemporary arts organization based in New York City. This organization was a reaction to the AIDS crisis during the late 1980s, where an urgent need arose to find a way to preserve and document artists and their artworks who live with or have passed away from AIDS. This collection contains a wide range of administrative materials created by Visual AIDS including correspondence, Board meeting minutes, office calendars, notes, publications, awards, press clippings, promotional materials, memorabilia, and analog audio and visual recordings. It also contains archived websites that document the organization's web presence beginning in 2016.
Work files within this collection represent an organization dedicated to creating and fostering AIDS awareness by showcasing artists with AIDS and their experiences through visual art projects, exhibitions, publications and special events. These work files typically contain notes, promotional material, correspondence, drafts, and photographs for these various projects and events, including The Ribbon Project, the Broadsides Project, Mapping No Boundaries, Share Your Vision, as well as events including A Big Fat Hairy Deal Benefit, VaVa Voom!, and gallery opening parties.
Documentation for Day With(out) Art, created to celebrate and mourn artists with AIDS or HIV positive on AIDS Awareness Day, includes posters, press clippings; promotional forms and fliers; and participant event promotional material. Planning files, participant forms, and photographs for a related event, Night Without Light, are also in this collection. Electric Blanket art installation notes, planning files, and venue promotional material are in this collection as well as original image slides and sound recordings used in the installation. The Archive Project material in this collection contains founding documentation for the project, exhibition files, and a small selection of individual artists' files.
AIDS (Disease); Safe sex in AIDS prevention -- History; AIDS activists -- New York (N.Y.); Artists -- New York (N.Y.) -- 20th century; Artists -- New York (State) -- New York -- 21st century; World AIDS Day; AIDS (Disease) and art -- United States.; Calendars.; Appointment books.; Minutes (administrative records); Slides (photographs); Color prints (photographs); Installations (Art) -- United States.; Artists and community -- United States; HIV/AIDS; AIDS awareness; Red ribbons (AIDS); LGBTQ+ arts; AIDS organizations; Visual AIDS (Organization); Kruger, Barbara, 1945-; Ligon, Glenn, 1960-; Reynolds, Hunter, 1959-2022; Blanchon, Robert, 1965-1999
- Series I. Administrative Records, 1988-2017; 13 Linear Feet in 8 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize flat boxes, and 1 item in a shared box
  Scope and Contents
  This series encompasses files documenting the overall operation and marketing efforts of Visual AIDS. It includes a variety of materials such as the archived website, correspondence, press clippings, and graphics for letterhead and logos. Additionally, the series contains office appointment calendars dating from 1999 to 2016, as well as minutes and notes from Board of Directors and Committee meetings. The organization's marketing and promotional materials feature posters, booklets, brochures, as well as branded items like promotional stickers, buttons, art notecards, and cloth tote bags, all showcasing artwork by artists such as Steve DeFrank, J. Morrison, Brian Kenny, Jessica Whitebread, and Kayrock. The series also includes a small selection of materials related to their 25th anniversary, including timelines, fact sheets, and commemorative note cards featuring original artworks.
  - Correspondence, 1988-2001 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Correspondence -- "Hate Mail", 1990-2017 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence -- "Fan Mail", 1999-2017 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National Endowment for the Arts AIDS Delegation Documents, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fact Sheets, Program Descriptions, Organizational History, Information Kits, 1989-1999 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
  - Press Clippings, 1989-1999 (Box 1, Folder 10, Box 65, Folder 3)
  - Press Clippings -- Visual AIDS 25th Anniversary, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Committees -- Steering Committee, 1989-1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Committees -- Slide and Registry Committee, May 1, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Committees -- PR Committee, January 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Committees -- AIDS Awareness Coalition, January 22, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Committees -- Benefit Committee, January 7, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Committees -- Exploratory Meeting to Address Needs of Artists Living with AIDS, January 27, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Committees -- Communications to Committees, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Committees -- Advisory Committee, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Committees -- List of Committees, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Mailing and Contact Lists, 1989-2016 (Box 2, Folder 10-14)
  - Awards and Proclamations -- New York State Governor's Arts Award Notification, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Budgets and Related, 1991-1994, 1996-1999, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 16-19)
  - Print Advertising -- Notes, Proofs, Published Ads, 1992-1994, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Board of Directors -- Minutes, Agendas, Member Lists, Notes, Correspondence, 1992-1998 (Box 3, Folder 4-35)
  - Board of Directors -- Minutes, Agendas, Retreat Material, Correspondence, 1999-March 2007 (Box 4, Folder 1-22)
  - Board of Directors -- Minutes, Agendas, Correspondence, May 2007 - April 2010 (Box 5, Folder 1-12)
  - New York State Council on the Arts -- Cultural Services Contract and Related, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Letterhead, Logo Graphics, circa 1994, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Founding Director Steps Down Press Release and Related, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Funding -- Lannon Grant Application, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Funding -- Source Lists and Notes, 1997-1998 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Commercial Space Search Form for Office, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Art + Newsletter, 1997-2004 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Cooper-Hewitt Museum -- Visual AIDS Donation of AIDS Educational Materials, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Announcement Card for Change of Address, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Executive Director (Barbara Hunt) -- Notebook, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Executive Director (Barbara Hunt) -- Appointment Book and Contact Cards, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Executive Director (Barbara Hunt) -- Notebook, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Executive Director (Nelson Santos) -- Appointment Book, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - National Association of Artists' Organizations (NAOO) Membership Material, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Promotional Material -- General Information Brochures, Booklets, Mailers, and Related, 1998, 2013-2016 (Box 6, Folder 5-8, Box 69, Folder 6-7)
  - Promotional Material -- Card for Limited Edition Benefit Print by Tony Feher, circa 2015 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Promotional Material -- Mailer "Spend Wisely. Fight AIDS", undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Website-Related Material -- Planning, The Body Website Agreement, 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
  - Office Appointment Books, 1999, 2003, 2005, 2007-2016 (Box 6, Folder 13-14, Box 7, Folder 1-5, Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Merchandise -- Buttons, Stickers, and Notecards, undated (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
  - New Executive Director Announcement -- Releases, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Staff Retreat -- Programming Notes, February 17, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Public New York -- Proofs for Letterhead, Envelopes, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Tote Bag with Art Graphic -- "AIDS Is Not Over!" by J. Morrison, 2009 (Box 63, Folder 1)
  - Tote Bag with Art Graphic -- "Cover the Stump..." by Steve DeFrank, 2010 (Box 63, Folder 2)
  - Tote Bag with Art Graphic -- "Can I Have Your Attention..." by Chloe Dzubilo and T De Long, 2011 (Box 63, Folder 3)
  - Tote Bag with Art Graphic -- "AIDS Is..." by Daryl Vocat, 2011 (Box 63, Folder 4)
  - Tote Bag with Art Graphic -- "AIDS On Going, Going On", 2013 (Box 63, Folder 5)
  - Tote Bag with Art Graphic (Tan) -- "Art / AIDS / Action" by Brian Kenny, 2014 (Box 63, Folder 6)
  - Tote Bag with Art Graphic (Black) -- "Art / AIDS / Action" by Brian Kenny, 2014 (Box 64, Folder 1)
  - Tote Bag with Art Graphic -- "Let's Hold Each Other..." by Shan Kelley, 2015 (Box 64, Folder 2)
  - Tote Bag with Art Graphic -- "I Want to Remember..." by Jessica Whitebread, 2016 (Box 64, Folder 3)
  - Tote Bag with Art Graphic -- "Unite Organize Resist" by Kayrock, undated (Box 64, Folder 4)
  - Visual AIDS 25th Anniversary -- Organization Timeline, Information Sheets, Promotional Cards, Quotes, 2013 (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
  - Staff, Board, and Committee Member Lists, circa 2013 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Archived Websites, February 2016-ongoing; 11 websites in 11 archived websites.
    Accruals
    https://visualaids.org/ is accrued semiannually. https://video.visualaids.org/ is accrued annually.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
    Appraisal
    Crawl was limited to domains and subdomains of visualaids.org in order to remain within the collection scope and data constraints.
    Scope was expanded to include Google documents.
    The Visual AIDS websites contain a database of works by artists with HIV/AIDS. The database features biographies of the artists as well as images of their art as well what exhibitions the art was featured in at Visual AIDS. The website also highlights the arts organization's projects, such as the Day Without Art, Love Positive Women, Women's Empowerment Art Therapy Workshops, the Red Ribbon Project, Last Address Tribute Walk, The Body As An Archive oral history project, Postcards from the Edge fundraiser, and the Visual AIDS Vanguard Awards (VAVA). The videos on the Day Without Art websites highlight work by HIV+ artists and artwork addressing issues around the AIDS pandemic. The video commissions website provides a complete archive of videos commissioned by Visual AIDS.
  - Personnel Manual, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Office Notes, Phone Messages, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Manhattan Proclamation Certificate -- Visual AIDS Day, June 20, undated (Box Shared Fales 109, Folder 20)
  - List of AIDS/Arts Services Organizations, undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Series II. Projects and Exhibitions, 1989-2017; 20 Linear Feet in 25 manuscript boxes, 5 small manuscript boxes, 3 oversized flat boxes, 4 flat-file folders, and 9 items in 3 shared boxes; 176.6 Megabytes in 80 computer files; 3 VHS; 1 audiocassette; 1 U-matic; 2 Betacam
  This series contains paper files and photographs in physical and digital format, as well as audio and video recordings created by Visual AIDS related to their events, projects, discussion series, and exhibitions. The materials document the organization's mission to foster dialogue and scholarship around the intersections of art, artists, and HIV/AIDS.
  The projects and partnerships represented in this series include The Ribbon Project (the origin of the red ribbon pin), with include press clippings, copyright documentation, and promotional materials. It also includes the Robert Blanchon Estate Project, comprised of book and exhibit catalog planning files, promotional materials, press clippings, and agreements. Artist projects sponsored by Visual AIDS are also included, such as the "AIDS is Not Over" stickers and postcards and the "Play Smart" trading card packets. Wall calendars in this series were created through various partnerships and projects, including those with Positively Art, Abbott Laboratories, and GlaxoSmithKline.
  Exhibitions of note in this series include Bodies of Resistance; Share Your Vision; Mapping No Boundaries; and Bearing Witness. Files related to these exhibitions include press clippings, promotional materials, installation photographs and instructions, as well as catalogs and related documents. This series also includes original memorial wall message cards from the Museum of Modern Art (MoMA) exhibition Projects: In Memory of….
  Events documented in this series include the A Big Fat Hairy Deal Benefit, My Bloody Valentine Benefit at L.U.R.E., VAVA Voom, Strike!, DaDa Ball, and exhibition opening parties. These event files typically include invitations, programs, planning documents, and photographs in physical and digital formats.
  Additionally, this series includes materials related to Visual AIDS' Broadsides — artist-designed graphics created from text, image, and informational artworks that were distributed as handouts, graphics, or billboards during the 1990s. These works were created by various artists, including Barbara Kruger, Glenn Ligon, John Giorno, and others. Broadside files contain drafts, proofs, final designs in various sizes, and related notes and correspondence.
  - An International Exhibition of AIDS Posters -- Information/Presentation Kit, 1989-1991 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Artist/Homeless Shelter Collaborative Project, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Positive Actions: The Visual AIDS Competition and Exhibit -- Press Releases, Notes, Posters, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 3, Box 69, Folder 1)
  - Under One Roof -- Holiday Store for AIDS Relief, 1990-1992 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Old Glory Condom Project by Jay Critchley, 1990-1993 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - The Witness Project -- Completed Forms, Lists of Artists, 1990-1994 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Project and Exhibit General Correspondence, 1990-2004 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Exhibit -- Visual AIDS II -- Promotional Cards, March 29 - April 19, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Exhibit -- Connecting Lives: Documents from the AIDS Crisis (Created from Electric Blanket) -- Promotional Material, Correspondence, Press Clippings, 1991-1993 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - The Ribbon Project -- Information Cards, Ribbon Pins, Fact Sheets, Poster, 1991, undated (Box 9, Folder 10, Box 67, Folder 16)
  - The Ribbon Project -- Forms, Letters, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - The Ribbon Project -- Artist's Statement and Graphics, circa 1991 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - The Ribbon Project -- Material Related to Tony Awards and Equity Fights Appearances, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - The Ribbon Project -- Mailing List, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - The Ribbon Project -- Honorary Committee Material, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - The Ribbon Project -- Press Clippings, 1991-1996 (Box 9, Folder 16, Box 10, Folder 1, Box 67, Folder 15)
  - The Ribbon Project -- Poster for Float in Heritage of Pride Parade, June 28, 1992 (Box 67, Folder 13)
  - The Ribbon Project -- Notebook with Meeting and Logo-Related Notes, circa 1992-1993 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - The Ribbon Project -- Council of Fashion Designers of America (CFDA) Award-Related, Event Program, 1992-1993 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - The Ribbon Project -- Identity Issues, Copyright of Ribbon Image and Use, 1992-1998 (Box 10, Folder 4-12)
  - The Ribbon Project -- Correspondence, 1992-1999 (Box 10, Folder 13)